William Temple Franklin-George Fox Collection 1791-1800 Mss.B.F86f
American Philosophical Society
William Temple Franklin-George Fox Collection
1791-1800
Mss.B.F86f
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
After William Temple Franklin returned to Europe in 1792, he left oversight of his financial interests in America in the hands of his intimate friend and fellow land speculator, George Fox. A physician and member of the American Philosophical Society, Fox also took possession of the remainder of Benjamin Franklin's papers, which eventually passed through his son, Charles Pemberton Fox, to the APS. The Franklin-Fox Collection contains 98 items, consisting mostly of letters from William Temple Franklin to George Fox regarding land holdings and finances, and retained copies of Fox's letters to Franklin. The correspondence is fairly relentlessly focused on business matters and rarely contains personal comments, however there are occasional requests for books and two reference to the yellow fever epidemic of 1798 and the death of Benjamin Franklin Bache.
0.25 linear feet
Fox, George, 1759-1828
Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
Biographical/Historical note
The sons of Joseph Fox and Elizabeth Mickle, George (1759-1828) and Samuel Mickel Fox I (1763-1808) became intimate friends of Benjamin Franklin's grandson William Temple Franklin. George, a physician who was elected a member of the American Philosophical Society in 1784, represented Philadelphia in the Assembly in 1800, and was an organizer and director of the Delaware and Chesapeake Canal and an early supporter of the bank of North America, of which he was Director from 1818 until 1828. Samuel also served in public office as a member of City Council, the Common Council (1793-1797), and the Upper Chamber (1797-1800), and he was both an incorporator of the Bank of Pennsylvania and its President from 1797-1808. After the Indian treaties of 1784 and 1785, Samuel and George invested heavily in lands in northern and western Pennsylvania, often investing with the Morrises and other Philadelphians. At his death, Samuel held 118,000 acres.
When Temple Franklin returned to Europe in 1792, he turned to his old friend George Fox to oversee his interests in America, particularly the land holdings he inherited and purchased from his father and grandfather. Franklin also left the balance of his grandfather's papers at Fox's estate Champlost, where they had been stored since Benjamin's death in 1790, and most of these were donated to the American Philosophical Society in 1840 after having passed to Fox's son Charles Pemberton Fox.
Scope and Contents note
As a fellow investor and overseer of William Temple Franklin's financial interests in the United States, George Fox had a detailed view of the investments of the beloved grandson of Benjamin Franklin. The Franklin-Fox Collection contains 98 items, consisting mostly of letters from William Temple Franklin to George Fox regarding land holdings and finances, and retained copies of Fox's letters to Franklin. The correspondence is fairly relentlessly focused on business matters and rarely contains personal comments, however there are occasional requests for books and two reference to the yellow fever epidemic of 1798 and the death of Benjamin Franklin Bache.
Related Archival Materials note
Several other collections at the APS relate to William Temple Franklin, including:
William Temple Franklin Papers
William Temple Franklin-Charles Pemberton Fox Collection
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Charles Pemberton Fox, 1840.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection has been microfilmed (Film 54-57).
Early American History Note
This collection of correspondence complements the much larger collection of William Temple Franklin Correspondence and the records and correspondence of George Fox, Franklin’s business agent and executor. This collection contains a series of letters from William Temple Franklin to George Fox that begins in the 1791 when W.T. Franklin was in London and ends in 1800. Most of the letters deal with Franklin’s business, especially his land speculations. There are two documents from Goveneur Morris that deal with business.
Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1769-1798; Fox, Charles Pemberton, 1792-1866; Fox, Joseph, ca.1710-1779; Fox, Samuel Mickle, 1763-1808; Jones, N. Cantwell; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816; Americans Abroad; Business Records and Accounts; Land and Speculation; Pennsylvania History; Philadelphia History; Real property--Pennsylvania; Yellow fever--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia
- William Temple Franklin-George Fox Collection, B F86f (Box 1)
  - Letter to George Fox, 1791 Feb. 18; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Scope and Contents note
    Enclosure for Mr. Barton.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1791 Feb. 26; ALS, 6p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial and land transactions. Political and social conditions in France and England.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1791 June 30; ALS, 8p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial transactions; mentions Gouverneur Morris.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1791 July 16; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Further financial instructions; mentions Gouverneur Morris and Robert Morris. Has sent all the news to B. F. Bache.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1791 Nov. 30; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Finances.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1792 March 11; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Introduces the bearer, Mr. Inman.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1792 March 12; ALS Cy, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Departure of Mr. Inman. Financial matters.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin. Recd, 1792 Mar 13; ALS, 1p.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816
    Investments.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1792 March 14; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1780-1823.
    Encloses note from Gouverneur Morris; finances.
  - Letter to [George Fox ?], 1792 April 4; LS Cy, 2p; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816
    Relative to sale of stock of U.S. [Bank] to William Temple Franklin.
  - Account with George Fox, 1791 Feb. 10-1792 April 5; D. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Contains note by George Fox (?).
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 Feb. 10, 11; ALS, 9p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Has just returned from trip to Scotland with Mr. Bache. Financial and land transactions; value of Pennsbury, possibility of his buying it. Hopes to complete edition of his grandfather's works within the year.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 March 15; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial matters.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 April 29; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial matters; mentions Cantwell Jones and R. Morris, Jr. Hopes to complete the printing of his grandfather's Works during the summer.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 June 5; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Finances. Orders copy of Bartram's Travels and other books.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 July 24; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 July 27; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Requests American seeds and apples be sent to him. News from France.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 Sept. 25; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial and land matters.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1793 Oct. 11; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Fox, London, 1794 Jan. 29; LS Cy, 7p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial and land transactions. Sends a desk and copying machine for Fox's use.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 March 1; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 April 10; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Fox; Burlington, 1794 May 12; ALS, 1p.; Ellis, Daniel
    Debts due to William Temple Franklin.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 July 6; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial and land transactions. Requests certain maps and books.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 July 12, 22; L.S and ALS, 6p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial and land transactions.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 July 15; ALS, 2p.; Jones, Cantwell
    Financial matters with William Temple Franklin.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 Aug. 8; ALS Cy, 7p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Finances. Plans to purchase landed estate near London. U.S.-British relations
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 Aug. 19; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Fox, 1794 Sept. 15; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to [George Fox], 1794 Dec. 12; L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to [George Fox], 1794 Dec. 16; L.S. 5p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial matters. Has sold his grandfather's library to Mr. Morris, jr.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1795 March 31; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial matters. The nuts and seeds arrived in good order, but the apples were rotten.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1795 April 28; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Contains note by G. Fox, June 13, 1795.
    Hopes to resell Shamokin lands. Forwards letter for Mr. Bingham.
  - Letter to George Fox, 1795 Aug. 12; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Fox, 1797 March 22; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Financial matters; sends his account. Desires to settle account with Jones.
  - Note relative to financial transactions involving Mr. [Robert] Morris [Jr.?], [Cantwell] Jones and [William Temple] Franklin, 1797 May 27; AN, 1p.; Fox, George 1759-1828
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1797 June 24; ALS, 2p.; Fox, George, 1759-1828
    General note
    FILM 54-57 FRAME 116
    William Temple Franklin's financial transactions with [Cantwell] Jones and Robert Morris, jr.
  - Letter to James A. Bayard, ca.1797 June; A.L. in 3d P. 3p.; Fox, George, 1759-1828
    Asks his opinion on financial difficulties involving William Temple Franklin, Cantwell Jones and Robert Morris, jr.
  - Letter to [William Temple Franklin], 1797 Dec 17; Dr. of A.L. 1p.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Relative to Northbrook and Jones debts.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1798 Jan. 1; A. dr. of L. 2p.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Same sheet contains drafts of letters dated Feb. 7, June 7, Dec. 8, 1798.
    William Temple Franklin's finances. Political and financial situation of the U.S.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1798 Feb. 7; ADr; Fox, George 1759-1828
    On same sheet with letter of Jan. 1, 1798.
    Franklin-Morris-Jones financial matters. Robert Morris threatened with ruin.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1798 June 7; ADr.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Land transactions of William Temple Franklin. Robert Morris in the debtors apartment; his son, Robert, has removed to Philadelphia.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1798 Dec. 9; ADr. On same sheet with letter of Jan 1, 1798.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    William Temple Franklin's financial and land transactions. Robert Morris. Yellow fever.
  - Letter to [William Temple Franklin], 1798 Dec. 11; ADr, 2p.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Same sheet contains drafts of letters dated Feb. 11, March 29, May 15, 1799, and Aug. 9, 1800. William Temple Franklin's financial and land transactions. Death of Benjamin Franklin Bache from yellow fever.
  - Letter to W.T F[ranklin], 1799 Feb. 11; ADr. On same sheet with letter of Dec. 11, 1798.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Requested by Robert Morris, jr. to evidence execution of a deed to William Temple Franklin for land in Northumberland co. Finances.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1799 March 29; ADr. On same sheet with letter of Dec. 11, 1798.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Necessity for making new copy of deed mentioned in letter of Feb. 11, 1799. William Temple Franklin's land transactions.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1799 May 15; ADr. On same sheet with letter of Dec. 11, 1798.; Fox, George, 1759-1828
    Has received from Robert Morris, Jr. sundry patents for land which is to be sold in Europe by William Temple Franklin. No prospect of William Temple Franklin's receiving debt owed by R. Morris and C. Jones.
  - Letter to [William Temple Franklin], 1800 Aug. 9; ADr. On same sheet with letter of Dec. 11, 1798.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Acknowledges print of founder of the Friends society; comments on. William Temple Franklin's land transactions.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, n.d.; ADr. 1p.; Fox, George 1759-1828
    Introduces Joseph Webb.